I am Ms. Frieren's student.
私は フリーレン様の弟子です
You pass.
合格だ
Next.
次
You're there like the wind
貴方は風のように
Closing your eyes at sunset
目を閉じては夕暮れ
I wonder what's on your mind
何を思っているんだろうか
Beyond Journey's End
With your eyelids open
目蓋を開いていた
貴方の目はビイドロ
Your eyes shone like glass
It faintly smelled like a sunny day
少しだけ晴るの匂いがした
晴れに晴れ 花よ咲け
Clear up the sky, let flowers bloom
Bloom and blame it on the sunny sky
咲いて晴るのせい
Even the rain, when it stops
降り止めば雨でさえ
貴方を飾る晴る
Will make you shine in the sunlight
Calm the stirring sounds in my heart
胸を打つ音よ凪げ
僕ら晴る風
We go like the sunny wind
あの雲も越えてゆけ
Go on and fly over that cloud
遠くまだ遠くまで
Further and further away
Denken the Imperial Mage.
I know all about you.
宮廷魔法使いのデンケン
お前のことはよく知っている
I'm honored.
それは光栄だな
A self-made military mage who rose to be
the most influential in the northern lands.
軍所属の魔法使いのたたき上げが
今や北側諸国で最も権力を持った魔法使いだ
It's an oft-heard heroic tale.
その美談はよく聞く
Honestly, I wish I could've met you
when you were still young,
正直 お前が若い頃に会いたかった
full of drive and ambition.
血の気と野心に満ちあふれた 若かりし頃に…
I have no interest in burnt-out ashes.
私は燃え滓には興味はない
Or so I believed.
そう思っていたのだがな
Do you feel differently now?
今は違うのか
When you saw me, you thought about
how you'd fight me, didn't you?
お前 私を見た時
どう戦うか考えただろう
Only for a moment.
I immediately abandoned the idea.
ほんの一瞬だけだ
すぐに諦めた
You pass. There's still a fire in you.
合格だ
まだ燃えている
Normally it wouldn't even occur
to someone to fight me.
普通は戦うだなんて発想は湧かない
Next.
次
You pass.
合格だ
What? But we haven't even spoken yet.
まだ何も話していないけど
会話が必要なのか
Do we need to?
I guess not.
それもそうだね
次
Next.
Is this some kind of joke?
お前 ふざけるなよ
What do you mean?
何が?
This is the first-class mage exam.
これは一級試験だぞ
What kind of idiot never even sets foot
into the examination grounds?
試験会場に一度も来ないバカがどこにいる
As you can see, my flesh-and-blood
body is here, too.
一応この通り…
生身の僕も試験会場に来ているよ
じゃなきゃ不参加で…
I wouldn't want to be disqualified.
Throughout the exam period, your actual
body never left your hometown.
この試験期間中
本体は故郷の村から出ていないな
Are you enjoying some tea right now?
今はのんびりティータイムか
I'm surprised.
驚いた
ユーベルにもバレなかったのに
Not even Übel noticed.
実にいい度胸だ
You've got guts. You pass.
合格
Next.
次
You're Wirbel, captain of
the Northern Magic Corps.
北部魔法隊隊長のヴィアベルだな
Of the second-class mages I know,
you're the most combat-oriented.
私の知る二級魔法使いの中では
一番の武闘派だ
With a single look, you realized
you couldn't beat me in battle.
私を一目見て
勝てない相手だと悟ったな
But that wasn't a judgment made out of fear.
だがそれは恐怖による判断ではない
An idiot prone to picking fights he can't win
wouldn't even make it to second-class mage.
勝てない勝負をするバカは
二級魔法使いにすらなれねえだろ
That's true.
それもそうだ
Tell me, what's your favorite spell?
好きな魔法を教えろ
Magic is a tool for killing.
魔法ってのは殺しの道具だぜ
I neither like nor dislike any spells.
好きも嫌いもあるか
You pass.
合格だ
Next.
次
What did you think when you saw me?
お前…
私を見てどう思った?
Um, I thought you were small and cute.
ええと…
小っちゃくてかわいいなと思いました
What's wrong with this year's test-takers?
今年の受験者はどうなってい…
You pass.
合格だ
Sense.
ゼンゼ
My apologies. We do have
a bumper crop this year.
すまなかったな
確かに今年は豊作だ
I failed.
落ちちゃった
次があるさ
There's always next time.
Stop following me.
もうついてくるなよ
Three years, huh?
３年後か
Ms. Frieren, I passed.
フリーレン様 受かりました
Well done.
よくやった
Frieren.
フリーレン
I made it this far because of you two.
ここまで来れたのはお前たちのおかげだ
Finally, I can visit a certain grave
in my hometown.
これで故郷に墓参りに行ける
I see.
そう
Hey, Fern.
なぁ フェルン
Have you decided yet?
まだかよ
これにしましょう 爺さんこれ…
I'd like—
Old man, I want these.
Well, well.
Don't be shy. Eat up.
遠慮せず食べなさい
When I was young, I hardly
ever got to eat sweet things.
儂の若い頃は 甘いものなんてめったに食べられなかった
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
What's going on here?
何 この状況
Have some, young man.
若造も食べろ
あぁ
Thanks, old man.
ありがとう 爺さん
Who is he?
誰なの
Mr. Denken the Imperial Mage.
宮廷魔法使いのデンケン様です
宮廷魔法使い…
An imperial mage?
You mean he's a noble?!
お貴族様じゃねえか!
I'm sorry for speaking so casually to you.
あの タメ口たたいてすみませんでした
It's fine. I came to this city
as a mage like any other.
構わん
儂は魔法使いとしてこの街に来た
でも 無関係な俺までごちそうしてもらうのは…
But you shouldn't feel obliged
to treat a stranger like me...
I have no other use for my money.
どうせ金の使い道などない
There must be something.
ないってことはないでしょ
He's right. Don't you have grandchildren?
そうです お孫さんとか…
儂には子も孫もおらん
I have no children or grandchildren.
儂が２０半ばの時に妻に先立たれた
My wife passed away when
I was in my mid-twenties.
She was always sickly.
元々体が弱かった
She was the daughter of a frontier noble
政争に敗れた
of the Northern Plateau who was
defeated in a political dispute.
北部高原の辺境貴族の令嬢でな
Back then, I was in need of both
wealth and influence.
あの頃の儂には 富も権力も必要だった
それしか 救う手だてを儂は知らんかった
Those were the only ways I knew to save her.
When Serie established the
Continental Magic Association
ゼーリエが特権を掲げて 大陸魔法協会を樹立したのは
and began offering the privilege,
it was just after my wife had already passed.
妻が亡くなって程なくしてからだ
I'd never felt more powerless.
あれほどの無力感はない
It's ironic. These days, I could
order entire nations around.
本当に皮肉なものだ
今では儂は 国ですら動かせるというのに
Fern.
フェルン
For me, magic was only ever a tool
to resolve political disputes.
儂にとって魔法は 政争の道具でしかなかった
Tell Frieren she reminded me
of how fun magic can be.
フリーレンに伝えてくれんか
魔法が楽しいものだったと
久々に思い出せた
The whole reason I became a mage was because
儂は勇者一行のフリーレンに憧れて
魔法使いになったんだ
I admired her deeds in the party of heroes.
You should tell her that yourself.
自分で伝えてください
I'm sure she'd be glad to hear it.
きっとフリーレン様も喜びますよ
You're right. That's what I'll do.
そうだな そうしよう
さすがは魔法都市オイサーストだね
The magical city of Äußerst didn't disappoint.
いい魔導書がいっぱい買えた
I bought a bunch of good grimoires.
Hey, old woman.
おいババア
You want those in this basket, right?
この籠に入れればいいのか
How could you just ignore her?
あれを無視はねえだろ
私だって少しは悩んだよ
Honestly, I did think about it a little.
Just a little?
少しだけか
I'm surprised. I thought one of Himmel's
party members would be...
意外なもんだな
勇者ヒンメルの仲間なら…
ヒンメルの仲間なら 何?
Would be what?
If anything, you surprised me.
私の方こそ意外だったかな
You tried to kill Fern's party
during the first test, didn't you?
第一次試験でフェルンたちを殺そうとしたんでしょ
Fern complained to me about it.
フェルン愚痴ってたよ
She said you seemed like someone
who'd kick a dog out of the way.
犬とか蹴っ飛ばしてそうなヤツだって
I get that a lot.
よく言われるわな
All I did was threaten them.
単なる脅しだよ
Though there was one of them whose death
would probably make the world a better place.
まぁ１人
殺しておいた方が世のためになりそうなヤツはいたけどな
I'd do anything to protect my hometown.
俺は故郷の村を守るためなら何だってする
I wanted to become a first-class mage for
the privilege of learning any spell I desired.
一級魔法使いになりたかったのも
望む魔法が与えられる特権のためだ
With a more powerful spell,
I can slaughter more demons.
強えぇ魔法が手に入れば
それだけ魔族をぶっ殺せるからな
But even in other parts of the world,
I do everything I can to help people in need.
でもな それと関係ない場所でも
困っているヤツがいたら
なるべく手を差し伸べるようにしているぜ
Why?
どうして?
My hometown is on the northern frontier.
俺の故郷は北の辺境でな
There are countless stories
about Himmel the Hero there.
勇者ヒンメルの逸話は いくらでも残っている
"千鏡の塔"の攻略
The conquest of the Thousand-Mirror Tower.
七崩賢"不死なるベーゼ"や
His battles against Böse the Immortal,
the Seven Sages of Destruction,
"皇獄竜"との戦い
and the Hell Emperor Dragon.
When I was a kid, I loved
those adventure stories.
ガキの頃の俺は そんな冒険譚が大好きだった
But the village elders hardly
ever talked about them.
でも村のジジババどもは
そんな話めったにしやがらねえ
They'd talk about how he defeated the monsters
やれ村を襲った魔物を退治しただの
that attacked the village,
or how he guarded some merchant,
やれ商人の護衛をしただの
ひどいものだと
or even how he just helped
carry stuff like a porter.
単なる荷物運びまであった
They were hardly impressive.
Just a bunch of boring stories.
全然大したことじゃねえ
つまんねえ話だ
そう思ったよ
That's what I thought, anyway.
But you could tell how happy the village
elders were when they told those stories.
なのに村のジジババは
心底うれしそうに
口をそろえてそんな話をするんだ
After Himmel the Hero died
勇者ヒンメルが死んで
and the remaining demons started
acting up, I finally understood.
魔族の残党が暴れ始めてからよく分かったよ
The Thousand-Mirror Tower, Böse,
the Hell Emperor Dragon,
確かに
千鏡の塔もベーゼも皇獄竜も
even the Demon King—none of that
had anything to do with my village.
魔王すら
俺の村には関係ねえわな
Everyone had their hands full
just maintaining their everyday life.
みんな 日々の生活を守るので手いっぱいだ
If Himmel the Hero
hadn't come to my village,
きっと 勇者ヒンメルが俺の村に来なかったら
then I doubt it'd still be there,
whether he saved the world or not.
世界が平和になっても
そこに俺の村はなかったんだろうな
I see. What are you trying to say?
そう 何が言いたいの?
Those stories of Himmel's less exciting
adventures were what guided me here.
俺をここまで連れてきたのは
勇者ヒンメルのくだらない冒険譚だ
That's all I'm trying to say.
俺が言いたいのはそれだけだ
I've been talking for too long.
少し長話が過ぎたな
I'm heading back with those guys.
結局あいつらと一緒に 帰ることになっちまった
フリーレン
Frieren, you should treasure
the encounters you have.
出会いは大切にしろよ
Death isn't the only goodbye in this life.
今生の別れってのは何も 死別だけじゃない
But I guess you already know that.
いや 百も承知か
Frieren, can't you magic us
across one by one?
フリーレン
魔法で向こうまで 順番に運んだりはできないのですか
Then I'd be left all alone on this side.
それだと私だけこっちに残っちゃうでしょ
Himmel, we need to defeat the
Demon King as soon as possible.
ヒンメル
俺たちは一刻も早く魔王を倒さねばならん
What point is there in helping people
in these insignificant ways?
こんな小さな人助けに 何の意味がある
You're right that they're insignificant.
確かに小さな人助けだ
Such deeds won't change the world.
きっとこんなことをしたって
世界は変わらない
But I won't ignore those in need
right in front of me.
でも僕は…
目の前で困っている人を見捨てるつもりはないよ
Don't worry, Himmel.
大丈夫だよ ヒンメル
The world has changed.
世界はちゃんと変わっている
We'll be granted our privileges tonight,
and we're each allowed to bring guests.
今夜特権の授与があるのですが
同伴者がいてもいいそうです
Since we have the opportunity,
let's all go together.
せっかくですし みんなで一緒に行きましょう
She looks really unhappy about the idea.
すごく嫌そうな顔してる
I was told we're allowed to bring guests.
あの 同伴者ありって聞いていたんですけど
I'm sorry, but Ms. Frieren
is prohibited per Ms. Serie.
申し訳ありません
ゼーリエ様からの通達で
フリーレン様は出禁です
For the next thousand years,
今後千年は
大陸魔法協会の施設には立ち入らないようにと
she is barred from entering any
Continental Magic Association facility.
What exactly did she do to deserve this?
フリーレン様が何をしたっていうんですか
It can't be helped.
I rubbed Serie the wrong way.
仕方がないよ
ゼーリエの機嫌を損ねてしまったからね
She's like a child.
まったく 子供みたいな人だよね
It's not as though
I wanted to be here anyway.
まぁ 私も来たくて来たわけじゃないし
I'll wait outside.
外で待っているね
俺も外で待ってるよ
I'll wait outside, too.
Hey.
That's the early evening bell.
宵の鐘だな
They should be done receiving
their privileges soon.
そろそろ特権の授与が終わる頃かな
Yeah.
ああ
A first-class mage.
一級魔法使い
The highest level of mage,
of whom fewer than fifty exist.
この世界で５０人もいない魔法使いの頂点か
Fern has grown so much.
フェルンも立派になったね
In this era, Fern will probably
become a more famous mage than me.
この時代では
きっとフェルンの方が有名な魔法使いになるんだろうね
フリーレン…
Frieren.
I'm glad.
うれしいね
Me too.
そうだな
フリーレン様
Ms. Frieren.
Who is he?
誰?
大陸魔法協会の人だね
A member of the Continental Magic Association.
I'm the first-class mage Lernen,
one of Ms. Serie's students.
一級魔法使いのレルネンです
ゼーリエ様の弟子の１人です
I'm sorry for the trouble
Ms. Serie has caused you.
ゼーリエ様がご迷惑をおかけしたようで
It's fine. She's always been like that.
構わないよ
昔からそういう人だったから
What is it, Frieren?
どうしたんだよ フリーレン
You can see the fluctuations
in my mana, can't you?
やっぱり見えているね 私の魔力の揺らぎが
You're incredibly skilled.
This peaceful era doesn't suit you.
とんでもない手だれだ
平和な時代には似つかわしくないね
そうですね
You're right. I am an old-fashioned mage
who only knows battle.
私は戦いしか知らない
時代遅れの魔法使いです
ゼーリエ様にもよく言われます
Ms. Serie often says the same thing.
魔王軍との戦火の時代に生まれていれば
If I'd been born during the era in which
we fought the Demon King's forces,
名だたる英雄たちと共に 歴史にその名を残したであろうと
I would've gone down in history
alongside the other famous heroes.
そう
I see. So what do you want from me?
それで私に何の用なの?
The only one of Ms. Serie's students
whose name is remembered is her first,
ゼーリエ様の弟子の中で
歴史に名を残したのは
もはやおとぎ話となった大魔法使いフランメのみ
the Great Mage Flamme
spoken of in fairy tales.
Once I grow old and die, yet another
proof of her existence will disappear.
私が老いて死ねば
あの方が生きた証しが
また１つ消えることになります
私はあの方を未来で １人孤独にさせたくないのです
I don't want her to be alone in the future,
even if it means going down in infamy
as the killer of the legendary mage Frieren.
たとえそれが
伝説の魔法使い フリーレン様を討ち取ったという
悪名であろうとも
I request a duel, Ms. Frieren.
手合わせを願えますか フリーレン様
I won't fight you. It'd be a waste of time.
手合わせはしないよ
時間の無駄だ
まったく
Honestly.
Mages who only know how to fight
can be so awkward.
戦いしか知らない魔法使いは
不器用な連中が多いんだから
There's no need for you to go down in history.
歴史に名を残す必要なんてないよ
Serie will remember you.
ゼーリエはちゃんと覚えている
One last thing.
最後に１ついい
This field of flowers was conjured by magic.
この花畑 魔法で作られたものだ
So what?
それがどうした
It was my master's favorite spell.
師匠が好きだった魔法だ
Didn't you call it useless?
くだらない魔法だって言っていなかったっけ
Honestly, Flamme was a failure.
正直フランメは 失敗作だった
Despite all her talent,
she failed to reach my heights.
あれほどの才を持ちながら
私ほどの高みへはたどり着けなかった
I taught many students after her.
その後もたくさんの弟子を取ったよ
Most died without ever reaching my level.
どれも私の足元にも及ばないままほとんどが先立った
But it's strange.
だが不思議なものだ
They were students I chose on a whim,
気まぐれで取ったはずの弟子なのに
but I can clearly recall each one's
personality and favorite spell.
一人一人の性格も
好きな魔法も鮮明に思い出せる
フリーレン
Frieren, for some reason, I've never
regretted taking on any of my students.
なぜか私は弟子を取って 後悔したことは一度もないんだ
Even if they never made their mark on history.
たとえ歴史にその名を残せずとも
She can't even tell her own students
how she truly feels.
自分の弟子にすら素直に気持ちを伝えられないんだ
本当に子供みたいな人だよ
She truly is a child.
フリーレン様
Ms. Frieren.
I received my privilege.
特権の授与が終わりました
じゃあ行こうか
Shall we go, then?
Ms. Frieren, how did you get
that injury on your shoulder?
フリーレン様
その肩のケガどうしたんですか
I'd better get it healed at the church.
教会で治療しないとね
まだやってるかな
Do you think they're still open?
Truly, we are awkward.
本当に不器用な人だ
Both you and I.
あなたも 私も
Stark, what are we gonna do today?
シュタルク 今日は何して遊ぶ?
Sorry, but I can't play today.
悪いな 兄ちゃん今日は遊べないんだ
Stark, did you have breakfast this morning?
シュタルク 朝飯は食ったか
I already ate.
もう食べたよ
Stark, have some of this.
シュタルク これ飲んでおいきよ
Hey, thanks.
ありがとう
The path of the warrior
is long and treacherous.
武の道は深く険しい
Take care.
達者でな
I will.
ああ
It's time to say goodbye to Äußerst.
これでオイサーストともお別れだね
People love you
everywhere you go, Mr. Stark.
シュタルク様はどこに行っても慕われていますね
Yeah?
そうか
By the way, Fern, what spell
did you end up asking for yesterday?
ところで フェルン
昨日はどんな魔法をもらったの?
Can't you tell?
分かりませんか
Your clothes are clean.
服がきれいになっている
And they smell vaguely floral.
それに何かフローラルな香りがする
Could it be...
これはまさか…
It's a spell to make clothes
clean and spotless.
"服の汚れをきれいさっぱり落とす魔法"です
This will make laundry a breeze.
これで洗濯が楽になります
Serie the Living Grimoire
lived up to her name.
さすがは生ける魔導書ゼーリエだね
That's a legendary-level spell
from the era of mythology.
神話の時代に存在したとされる伝説級の魔法だよ
でかした フェルン
Well done, Fern.
That's my student.
それでこそ私の弟子だ
Of course, Ms. Frieren.
当然です フリーレン様
Ms. Serie didn't seem at all
happy about it, though.
ゼーリエ様は すごく嫌そうな顔をしていましたけどね
Are you insane?
正気か お前
I'm sure. Serves her right.
だろうね いい気味だ
They're here.
来た
Frieren, thank you for everything.
フリーレン
本当にありがとうね
We didn't pass this time,
but we'll try again in three years.
私たちは不合格だったけれども
３年後また頑張ることにするよ
I see. That's good.
そう よかった
It's been fun.
楽しかったよ
Take care.
元気でね
じゃあまたね
See you later.
Yeah. See you later.
またね
That was a rather quick goodbye,
just like with Sein.
ザイン様の時もそうでしたけど
随分あっさり別れますね
クラフトの時もだ
And Kraft.
Himmel, you always say quick goodbyes.
ヒンメルってさ
すごくあっさり人と別れるよね
You think that's strange?
変かな
It doesn't seem like you.
まぁ らしくないとは思うな
It was just a side job, but we still
spent two weeks traveling together.
依頼とはいえ
２週間も旅路を共にした仲だ
And we drank with him practically every night.
それに 彼とは毎晩のように酒を酌み交わして
それはもう…
You corrupt priest.
生臭坊主
You're right.
そうだね
And you alright
But I'm sure we'll run into each other again
if we continue traveling.
でも旅を続けている以上
Can you hear me
また会うことだってあるだろう
Trailing along deserted train tracks
Tearful goodbyes aren't our style.
涙の別れなんて僕たちには似合わない
Crying excessively
Wanting you to smile
After all, it would be embarrassing
when we met again.
だって また会ったときに恥ずかしいからね
I hold on to memories I'd like to keep fresh
さよならよりずっと大切な
There's something I'd like to tell you
言葉で伝えたいんだ
With words more precious than a goodbye
ありふれてでも特別で
Unremarkable yet special
ほらこの目じゃなければ
See, things that couldn't have been
見えなかったものだ
Seen if it weren't for these eyes
どうして溢れてく
Why? They begin to overflow
だからもう一度生まれ変わろうとも
So, if I were to be born again
I would surely choose this place once more
また私はここを選ぶんだろう
だからあなたとまた巡り逢ったら
So, if we were to meet again
もう離さない今を選ぶんだろう
I'd never let you go, I'd choose the present
約束なんてなくても
Even if no promises were made
孤独に迷う日々でも
Even if I'm lost in days of loneliness
その涙だって大丈夫
Those tears will be alright,
dawn will surely break
きっと夜が明けるよ
I'm whispering our lullaby
for you to come back home
It would be embarrassing when we met again.
また会ったときに恥ずかしいからね
What does that mean?
何ですか それは
Episode 28: It Would Be Embarrassing When We Met Again